Guide to the Robert E. Middleton Papers, 1939-1954
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Robert E. Middleton Papers
1939-1954
Middleton, Robert, 1920-
0.75 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, photographs and miscellaneous papers from Robert E. Middleton, VC Professor of Music 1953-1985.
Biographical Note
Born 18 Nov 1920 in Diamond, Ohio, Robert E. Middleton was a composer, performing artist and instructor. Educated at Harvard, Middleton began teaching music at Vassar College in 1953, after spending three years as an instructor at Harvard. Command Performance, Middleton's full-length opera was commissioned by the Vassar College Centennial Committee and had its premiere at Vassar College on 11 Nov 1961. In 1974, Middleton was appointed the George Sherman Dickinson Chair of the Music Department. He retired on 30 June 1985.
Chronology
18 Nov 1920 Born in Diamond, Ohio
Sept 1942-Jan 1946 Military Service, U.S. Army
1948 B.A., Harvard University
1953 Appointed Assistant Professor, Vassar College
1954 M.A., Harvard University
1958 Appointed Associate Professor, Vassar College
1965 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship in Musical Composition
1966 Appointed Full Professor, Vassar College
1974 Appointed George Sherman Dickinson Professor, Vassar College
30 June 1985 Retired from Vassar College
Scope and Content Note
The Robert E. Middleton collection contains correspondence, notes, postcards and 2 scores.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the
Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Boulanger, Nadia; Chanler, Theodore, 1902-1961; Chauncey, Henry; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975; Palmer, Robert, 1915-; Piston, Walter, 1894-1976; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995; Szigeti, Joseph, 1892-1973; Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984
Subjects:
Composers; Pianists; Musicians; Opera--United States--20th century; College teachers
Document Types:
Postcards; Scores (documents for music); Photographs
VCL Categories
Music; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Finding aid encoded by Jason Kovari, 12 Feb 2009.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert E. Middleton, 1992. 1950 score donated by the Paddock Music Library, Dartmouth College, 2016.
Appraisal
The Robert E. Middleton Papers were appraised by Wurlitzer-Bruck, 60 Riverside Dr., New York, New York 10024, 1 July 1992.
Container List
- "Approximations for Viola and Piano" by Robert Middleton, 1970; (1 score) (1.1)
- Boulanger, Nadia, 1939-1946; (14 notes and letters from N.B.; 1 letter from Henry Chauncey, Harvard University) (1.1b)
- Boulanger, Nadia, 1952-1958; (18 notes and letters; 2 postcards (1.2)
- Boulanger, Nadia, circa 1960-1969; (11 notes and letters; 2 photographs) (1.3)
- Boulanger, Nadia, 1970-1979; (12 notes and letters) (1.4)
- Chanler, Theodore, 1947; (2 letters) (1.5)
- Chanler, Theodore — Score of Second Joyful Mystery, circa 1947 (1.6)
- "Command Performance: opera in four acts", approximately 1960; (typescript) (1.6b)
- "The Complete Libretto of Command Performance" by Robert Middleton and Harold Smith, 1961; (program for permier performance laid in) (1.6c)
- Copland, Aaron, 1964, 1969; (4 letters) (1.7)
- Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1953-1958; (6 letters) (1.8)
- "Organ Preludes" by Robert Middleton, 1979; (1 score) (1.8b)
- Palmer, Robert, 1965 (1.9)
- Piston, Walter, 1957-1966; (12 letters; 1 postcard) (1.10)
- Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1958 (1.11)
- Szigeti, Joseph, 1956-1958; (3 letters from Szigeti; 1 carbon from Middleton; 1 program) (1.12)
- Thompson, Randall, 1958, 1964; (2 letters; 1 postcard) (1.13)
- "String Quartet" by Robert Middleton, 1950; (1 score) (Box 2)